<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="john@jbrugge.com">John Brugge</author>
    <title>Glean : In The Works</title>
  </properties>

<body>
<section name="In The Works">
<p>
Some tools have trickier dependencies or rely less on convention, and are a bit
more work to script in a general way. Others are tools I'd like to have scripts for
but just haven't gotten around to. These tools are ones on my to-do list.
If there are others that you use and would like to see included, just
<a href="mailto:john.brugge+glean@gmail.com">let me know</a>.
</p>
<table class="bodyTable">
<th>Name</th><th>Description</th><th>Dependencies</th>
<tr class="a"><td><a href="http://www.hackystat.org/hackyDevSite/home.do">hackystat</a></td><td>Collection and analysis of feedback metrics</td><td></td></tr>
<tr class="a"><td><a href="http://www.hibernate.org/255.html">hbm2doc</a></td><td>Hibernate mapping documentation</td><td></td></tr>
<tr class="a"><td><a href="http://cwiki.apache.org/S2PLUGINS/sitegraph-plugin.html">sitegraph</a></td><td>Struts 2.0 page flow visualization</td><td>Struts 2</td></tr>
<tr class="a"><td><a href="https://sorcerer.dev.java.net/">sorcerer</a></td><td>Source code cross reference generator</td><td>Java 6</td></tr>
<tr class="a"><td><a href="https://taglibrarydoc.dev.java.net/">taglibrarydoc</a></td><td>Javadoc for JSP taglibs</td><td></td></tr>
<tr class="a"><td><a href="http://www.lumrix.de/xsbrowser.php">xsbrowser</a></td><td>Documentation and browsing of DTD or XML schema</td><td></td></tr>
<tr class="a"><td><a href="http://xframe.sourceforge.net/xsddoc/index.html">xsddoc</a></td><td>Documentation for XML schema</td><td></td></tr>
</table>
</section>

<section name="Features">
<p>
Along with new tools, there are other ways I would like to see Glean extended.
I want to keep it simple, with as few demands on projects as possible, so the
ideas here are mostly incremental improvements. Ant properties-based configuration
is already complex enough. 
<ul>
<li>Integrating with continuous integration servers (CruiseControl, Hudson)</li>
<li>Supporting projects that have multiple source folders</li>
<li>Better XSLTs for some of the tools (e.g. FindBugs)</li>
<li>Other ways to publish the output so that it could be included in a project website</li>
<li>A way to support tools that have multiple output options. For example, JDepend
can generate a traditional tabular report or a DOT-based graph rendered by Graphviz</li>
<li>Provide a way to discover the appropriate Glean settings for a given project automatically.
That is, to look for common directory layouts and build a properties file for you.</li>
<li>Include Groovy scripting to allow more control within the scripts</li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
