<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="john@jbrugge.com">John Brugge</author>
    <title>Glean : Tool Installation</title>
  </properties>

<body>
<section name="Getting The Tools">
<p>
If you don't have the tools installed already that Glean uses, you can get them
a couple of different ways. The <a href="tools.html">tools</a> page has a list of
download links that get you to that tool's site, and you can follow their instructions
for download and setup. 
</p>
<p>
There is also an Ant script in the Glean installation
that is able to download about a dozen of the tools from public Maven repositories.
It requires the Maven Ant tasks be installed, which is just one manual download,
compared with a dozen. The script will also generate a properties file for Glean
telling it where each of these tools is installed.
<ul>
<li>Download the <a href="http://maven.apache.org/ant-tasks.html">Maven Ant tasks</a>
and install them where Ant knows about them (instructions are on the Maven Ant tasks
page)</li>
<li>Run the Glean Ant script. By default, the tools will go to a directory under
<code>${user.home}/temp</code>, and a <code>toolhome.properties.local</code>
file will be created in the same place.
<pre>
ant -f get-tools.xml
</pre>
</li>
<li>You can specify the root of the tools area as well as the location of the
generated properties file with properties on the command line.
<pre>
ant -f get-tools.xml \
    -Dtools.base=/path/to/tool/base/dir \
    -Dtoolhome.props=/path/to/toolhome.properties.local
</pre>
</li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Defining Tool Homes">
<p>
Glean uses a pair of properties files to tell it where each of the tools it uses
can be found. 
<ul>
    <li>The file <code>toolhome.properties</code> comes with Glean, and
defines some defaults that may or may not correspond to your particular installation.</li>
    <li>The file <code>toolhome.properties.local</code>, if it exists, is read before the
default file and is meant to let you define where your particular tools are if
they differ from the default locations.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
These files are simple properties files, with the convention that the property
name is
<pre>
(Glean tool name)home.properties
</pre>
Glean uses this convention to set up the tasks and paths needed for that tool to run.
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>

